<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A discovery of the first wisdom from beneath, and the second wisdom from above. Or, The difference betwixt the two seeds, the one after the flesh, the other after the spirit. With the true worship of God after the spirit, and the false worship of the world, who lives in outward forms, useth customes and traditions, not knowing the onely true God that dwelleth in his saints, and rules by his spirit of power, which causeth them to differ from the world, and those that have the form of godlinesse, and want the power thereof. ... Written by a servant of the Lord, whom the world scornfully nicknameth, and calleth a Quaker, who is prisoner for the testimony of the truth at Applebie in Westmorland, whose name is James Nayler.</title>
            <author>Naylor, James, 1617?-1660.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1656</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 77 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A89835</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing N272</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E693_4</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R207000</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99866077</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99866077</idno>
            <idno type="VID">118337</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A89835)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 118337)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 107:E693[4])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A discovery of the first wisdom from beneath, and the second wisdom from above. Or, The difference betwixt the two seeds, the one after the flesh, the other after the spirit. With the true worship of God after the spirit, and the false worship of the world, who lives in outward forms, useth customes and traditions, not knowing the onely true God that dwelleth in his saints, and rules by his spirit of power, which causeth them to differ from the world, and those that have the form of godlinesse, and want the power thereof. ... Written by a servant of the Lord, whom the world scornfully nicknameth, and calleth a Quaker, who is prisoner for the testimony of the truth at Applebie in Westmorland, whose name is James Nayler.</title>
                  <author>Naylor, James, 1617?-1660.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>39, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Giles Calvert, at the Black Spread-Eagle at the West end of Pauls.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1653.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Aprill. 25".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Society of Friends --  Doctrines --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Mind and body --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Wisdom --  Religious aspects --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:118337:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A DISCOVERY OF THE Firſt <hi>WISDOM</hi> from beneath, AND THE Second <hi>WISDOM</hi> from above.</p>
            <p>OR, The difference betwixt the two Seeds, The one after the <hi>Fleſh,</hi> the other after the <hi>Spirit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>WITH The true worſhip of God after the Spirit, and the falſe worſhip of the world, who lives in outward Forms, uſeth Cuſtomes and Traditions, not knowing the onely true God that dwelleth in his Saints, and rules by his Spirit of Power, which cauſeth them to differ from the world, and thoſe that have the form of godlineſs, and want the power thereof.</p>
            <p>Alſo the ſubtilty of the Serpent ruling in the hearts of the Children of Diſobedience, diſcovered.</p>
            <p>And a call to repentance to all that run on in blindneſs, dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and ignorance, and the judgement that is due to all thoſe that will not take counſell of the Lord, but turn the Grace of God into wantonneſs.</p>
            <p>Written by a Servant of the Lord, whom the world ſcornfully nicknameth, and calleth a <hi>Quaker,</hi> who is priſoner for the teſtimony of the Truth at <hi>Applebie</hi> in <hi>Weſtmorland,</hi> whoſe name is JAMES NAYLER.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Giles Calvert,</hi> at the Black Spread<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Eagle at the Weſt end of <hi>Pauls.</hi> 1653.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:118337:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:118337:2"/>
            <head>A Diſcovery of the firſt Wiſdom from beneath, and the ſecond Wiſdom from above, or, The difference betwixt the two <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eeds, the one after the fleſh, the other after the Spirit.</head>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <head>I. <hi>The Wiſdom from beneath which leadeth into bondage, and the Wiſdom from above which leadeth up into per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect libertie, where there is freedom and Communion with the Father and the Son.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Ear friends, all minde your guide within you, even the pure light of God, which bears witneſs againſt all your ungodly wayes, ungodly words, thoughts, works and worſhips, which are after the world, and leads you without from the Lord your guide, for what ſtands in outward things, deviſed in the will and brain which is the Serpents ſeal, is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſed from God, kept out of the Kingdom, where the earthly will hath libertie, leads out to viſible things and feed upon duſt, which is the Serpents meat; but you who deſire to be fed with that which is Eternall, lay aſide all your wiſdom which is naturall, for the naturall man receives not the ſpirituall things of God,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:118337:3"/>
for that wiſdom ſhall never know God which ſtands in the will of man, but darkens the pure light in you and oppoſeth it, and if you abide in the pure light within, you ſhall ſee, that what ever the light of Chriſt makes appear to be evil and to be caſt off, then the other light which ſtands in mans wiſdom, makes a cover for it that it may abide ſtill, and thus the fleſh luſteth againſt the ſpirit, and that wiſdom which ariſeth out of the earth oppoſeth that which is from above, and cals evil good, and good evil, and the wo being upon that na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, you can have no peace, while that ſtands, and from hence comes all your troubles and darkneſs with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in you, becauſe that eye which is open to the viſible offends, and here you are ſhut out of the Kingdom, which conſiſts in righteouſneſs, peace, and Joy in the holy Ghoſt: but were that eye pluckt out, and you turned within to ſee with that eye that is ſingle, then the whole body would be full of light, and abiding in that light, it will ſhew you a path that leads to puritie and Holineſs, without which none ſhall ever ſee the Lord: And it will let you ſee a Law written in your hearts, even the righteous Law of the new Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, which is a Book ſealed to all the wiſdom of the World, and none can read it but the pure light that gave it forth, which light as it ariſeth in you, it will open all Parables and read all Scriptures within you in your meaſure, and ſo you will come to the Unitie with all Saints in meaſure, and ſo come to Chriſt the firſt born, even to the innumerable company of Angels, to the ſpirits of juſt men made perfect, and to God the Judge of all, where no Serpents wiſdom ſhall ever come; and that Law being laid open, will be a limit to the carnall minde, when it would run forth, and the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:118337:3"/>
Judge will appear, who will paſſe true judgement upon all things as they are within you, and a ſeparation will be made between the precious and the vile in you, and you will be brought to diſcern, what leads to obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and what leads to diſobedience, and here is your true Teacher whereby all ſhall be taught of God, as ſaith the Scripture, and minding this light it will ſhew you a Croſſe, to be daily taken up, whereby all the unruly nature muſt be crucified, for all muſt be brought ſubject to the yoke, even the moſt rebellious and ſtif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>necked in you, for he will tread upon the neck of Kings, and that which hath captivated the pure in you, muſt go into captivity, for now the Lord is Riſen to diſquiet the earth and them that are at reſt, yea wo to them that are at eaſe in Sion, for he is riſen who is to rule all Nations with a rod of Iron, and to deliver the oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and to ſet open the priſon doors, and to ſet the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners free, that they may ſerve him and praiſe his name, even the name of the Lord, Holy and pure, bleſſed for evermore. And dear friends be faithfull in what you know, take heed of making a profeſſion of what you are not, and ſo you be found diſſemblers before the Lord, but keep low in meekneſs and patience, ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the will of God in all things, and all thoſe ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies that will not that Chriſt ſhould raigne over them, bring them before the Judge that they may be ſlain, even upon that Croſſe that is daily to be taken up, for the Croſs is to the carnal, wilde, heady, bruitiſh nature in you, which lies above the ſeed of God in you, and oppreſſeth the pure, now giving this up to be crucified makes way for that which is pure to ariſe, and guide your minds up to God, there to wait for power and ſtrength againſt whatſoever the light of God makes
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:118337:4"/>
manifeſt to be evil, and ſo to caſt it off, and ſo you ſhall ſee where your ſtrength l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>th and who it is in you, that worketh the w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>l and the deed, and then you ſhall be brought into a poſſeſſion of what you have but had a profeſſion, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>inde the power of what you have had but in words, which is hid from all profeſſions in the World, and is revealed no other way, but by the pure light of God dwelling in you and you in it: take heed of ſearching into the hidden things of God, by your own wiſdom, which is carnal, for that hath God ſhut out of the Kingdom, and ſeparated it from him, and the things of God and his Kingdom are hid from it, and it is appointed for utter darkneſs, accurſed from him, and doth oppoſe him in all things and in all ages, the wiſdom of the great men of the earth have perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted the pure wiſdom of God, and counted it fooliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and God hath ſaid this ſhall come to nought, and abiding in the pure light of Chriſt within, you ſhall ſee that ſame wiſdom in your ſelves, will be conſulting and leading you any way, rather then to wait on the pure light, and this hath been a tempter from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, and hath eaten of the forbidden fruit, and that which hath eaten of the tree of knowledge, muſt not taſte of the Tree of Life, but ſhall ſurely die, and the flaming ſword is to this wiſdom, therefore turn your minds within and waite for a wiſdom from above, which begins with the fear of the Lord, which is pure, peaceable, gentle and eaſie to be entreated, and if you keep your eye to this you ſhall ſee as this growes which is pure, there will be a death to that which is ſenſuall and carnal, and of the Serpent; and as you grow in this pure, you will grow in the knowledge of Chriſt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in you, and this is not to be attained by ſeeking with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:118337:4"/>
here and lo there, but onely by keeping your eye within to the inviſible, and giving diligent ear to that voice that ſpeakes to the ſoul, and ſpirit, for the miniſtry of Chriſt is to the ſpirit in priſon, not to the outward, but to the inward man, which is led captive and impriſoned, by that Scrpentine wiſdom that rules in the outward, and by which it is kept in death, which once coming to hear the voice of Chriſt, it is raiſed from death to life, and then that Scripture is fulfilled, the dead hear the voice of the Son of God, and they that hear ſhall live, and this being once reſtored to life, is that which hath fellowſhip with the Father and the Son, yea it is one with them; and this is that which as it ariſeth, overcomes the world in you, gets the victory obtains the Crown, for it is the promiſed ſeed, and heir of all the promiſed in this life, and that which is to come, but there is no agreement between this and the ſeed of the Scrpent, for where ever the Scrpents wiſdom ſeekes after, it is that he may ſlay it, but God hath hid it from him, and doth hide it out of the Scrpents ſight, but that ſeed ſees the Scrpent where he is, and doth judge him and condemn him, and bruiſe his head: how deep are thy Counſels, Oh Lord, paſt finding out.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>James Nayler</hi> priſoner for the name of Chriſt at <hi>Appleby;</hi> wiſheth grace and Peace.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:118337:5"/>
               <head>II. <hi>All labouring and ſtriving by forms, cuſtomes, and tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, comes ſhort of that worſhip in Spirit and in Truth. The wayes the two men walk in,</hi> viz. <hi>the Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall and the carnall, the difference betwixt them, and how you may know them by their fruits.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>ALl men and women that make a profeſſion, and go under the name of <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> &amp; ſay you love Jeſus Chriſt, mind him whom you profeſs, that you may be taught by him in all your ways and worſhips, and do not ſuffer your ſelves to be deceived any longer by<note place="margin">Eph. 4. 14.</note> fair ſpeeches, and flattering high notions, by which you have been blinded for many years, and led on to worſhip God in outſide forms and cuſtoms, after the traditions and commandements of men, which by imaginary imitations and conſultations they have ſet up for their own ends, and have made laws to bind the people to obſerve them, contrary to that light ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning into the conſcience (the throne of Chriſt) and the practice of Chriſt and his Apoſtles, and ſo have made the <hi>word of God</hi> of none effect by their traditions;<note place="margin">Pſal. 94. 20.</note> but neither they nor you have known the true God,<note place="margin">Mark 7. 13.</note> who is worſhipped in ſpirit: for whoſoever ſinneth hath<note place="margin">1 John 2. 4.</note> 
                  <note place="margin">1 John 2. 3.</note> not ſeen him, nor known him; He that ſaith, I know<note place="margin">1 John 1. 3. 6.</note> him, and keepeth not his commandements, is a lier, nor have you fellowſhip with him, nor did ever you receive an anſwer of acceptance from him, though you have been worſhippers in your formal cuſtoms all your time, and have many times afflicted your ſelves from morning till evening, yet no anſwer.
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:118337:5"/>
And herein how much you have reſembled thoſe four<note place="margin">I Kings 18. 26. 29.</note> hundred worſhippers in <hi>Elias</hi> time, if ever your eyes be open, you will ſee. But the living God is not as the dumb Idols to thoſe who know him: for whom he ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts he anſwers, and hath done in all ages, and they<note place="margin">Pſal. 65. 4, 5.</note> 
                  <note place="margin">Jonah 2. 2.</note> are brought into union with him, and know him, and<note place="margin">Pſal. 66. 18, 19.</note> how he will be worſhipped, not by hearſay, but from<note place="margin">Iſa. 54. 13.</note> him alone, and their worſhip is not an imitation by<note place="margin">Rom. 10. 8.</note> 
                  <note place="margin">John 10. 14.</note> the letter, but they are all taught of him, every one<note place="margin">Gen. 4. 5.</note> in his meaſure, and they walk and worſhip him by his<note place="margin">Prov. 15. 8.</note> 
                  <note place="margin">Prov. 21. 4.</note> word, and the word is nigh them, in their hearts, in<note place="margin">Hag. 2. 13, 14.</note> their mouths, by which they are guided, and they know<note place="margin">Pro. 3. 33.</note> 
                  <note place="margin">John 3. 3, 5, 6.</note> his voice; but theſe are ſheep, ſuch as are born again,<note place="margin">I Cor, 15. 48, 49.</note> of the Spirit, not after the will of man, but after the will of God. But there is a generation whoſe ſacrifice<note place="margin">G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l. 5. 17,</note> God doth not accept, whoſe praiers are abomination, and whoſe plowing is ſin, who pollute all they meddle with, who are hated of the Lord, whom Chriſt praies not for; for they, their ſacrifice, and all they do are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſed from God, &amp; theſe are in the firſt birth children of wrath, and enemies to God. Now all people try your ſelves, whether you be in the firſt birth, or you be born again: there is a firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> and there is a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond <hi>Adam,</hi> and they who are in the firſt, bear his Image; and they who are in the ſecond, beare his Image, and as is the earthly, ſuch are they that are earthly; and as is the heavenly, ſuch are they that are heavenly, and theſe are contrary one to the other, the one being from above, the other being from below; the one the ſeed of God, the other the ſeed of the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, and an enmity is put between them by God, and<note place="margin">Gen. 3. 15.</note> there can be no uniting them in one, for what concord hath Chriſt with <hi>Belial,</hi> or the believer and the unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liever?</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:118337:6"/>The firſt man is of the earth earthly, minds earthly things, lives in the earth, delights in the earth, luſts after the earth, covets, contends &amp; ſues for it, for his treaſure is in the earth, and his heart is with it; for it is his por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and his thoughts, words, and wiſdom are all im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed about it, plotting and forecaſting how to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs it, and fetch it out of the hands of others to heap up, but is never ſatisfied, but is a ſervant to it: it is his life, his joy: if it be taken from him, his comfort is gone: it is his God, and he worſhips it, and would have all to worſhip him becauſe of the abundance of it that he hath got together: for he knows no other God, nor<note place="margin">Exod. 5. 2.</note> greater happineſs then what he ſees with carnall eyes, &amp; this all his actions witneſs; and this is he that is exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted above all that is called God, and oppoſeth God in<note place="margin">2 Theſſ. 2. 4.</note> all his commands: When God faith, <hi>Thou ſhalt not</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 2. 17.</note> 
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 3. 4, 5.</note> 
                  <hi>oat of the Tree of knowledge, for if thou do, thou ſhalt die;</hi> he ſaith, You may eat of it, and not die, but live bet<note place="margin">Matth 4. 10.</note> ter, be as God himſelf. When God ſaith, <hi>Thou ſhalt</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Exod. 20. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>not bow down nor worſhip any Creature in heaven or earth, for I am jealous of mine honour, and will not have it given to any creature, but will viſit that ſin to the third and fourth generation;</hi> he ſaith, Thou ſhalt bow down and<note place="margin">Luke 4. 5, 6, 7, 8,</note> worſhip me, and thou ſhalt gain by it, and be received into the kingdoms of the Earth, and the glory of them, (for there I am Prince) and I will beſtow great things upon thee: But if thou wilt not, I make a Decree,<note place="margin">I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eſter 3.</note> ſign it with my own Ring, and ſet all my ſervants to act it, that all thy ſeed ſhall be cut off out of my Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions in one day. And thus to oppoſe God, and ſeek to deſtroy his ſeed where it appears, hath been his way from the beginning, and is his way at this day, and here are all you haters, enviers and perſecuters, and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:118337:6"/>
you are doing his worke, and you are acted by him who was a murtherer from the beginning.</p>
               <p>The ſecond man is the Lord from Heaven, and he that bears his Image minds heavenly things, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights in heavenly things; for he is ſpirituall, and judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth<note place="margin">I Cor. 15 47.</note> 
                  <note place="margin">Col. 1. 15.</note> not according to outward appearance; for the evill eye that offends is pluckt out, that eye which leads in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to viſible things; and there is an eye turned inward,<note place="margin">Pſal. 25, 14.</note> which pierceth into the hidden treaſure which is eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, which the naturall eye ſees not; and having once got a ſight of the true riches, he caſts away all his Idols and Idol worſhips, and what ever is periſhing, and treads upon all that may hinder his enjoyment thereof, though they have been never ſo dear unto him, now it is become baſe droſs and dung, that he may obtain the<note place="margin">Phil. 3. 8.</note> inviſible riches: and then the firſt born, whoſe heart is in the earth, calls him a fool and a mad man, and thinks it ſtrange that he will not ſerve the world nor the times for money, nor have mens perſons in admiration<note place="margin">Jude 16.</note> becauſe of advantage, nor obſerve the Heatheniſh cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes for fear of men, but is made to declare againſt them in open ſtreets and markets; and then that na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture<note place="margin">Acts 14, 16.</note> which lives in theſe things, takes up ſtones to caſt at him, &amp; cries againſt him in tumults, Away with him, it is not fit he ſhould live, for he breaks all cuſtomes and traditions, which we and our Fathers have lived in ſo many years, and turns the world up-ſide down, but being blind, cannot ſee that the Lord is in him, who<note place="margin">Acts 16. 20, 21.</note> counts all the cuſtoms of the Heathen vain, and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turns Kingdoms and Nations at his will, and thereby makes way for him to reign whoſe right it is.</p>
               <p>The firſt man worſhips a <hi>God</hi> at a diſtance, but knows him not, nor where he is, but by relation from others,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:118337:7"/>
either by word or writing; and as he receives his know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge<note place="margin">1 John 2. 4.</note> of him from men, ſo his worſhip towards him is<note place="margin">1 John 2. 6.</note> taught by the precepts of men; and if men, on whom<note place="margin">Iſa. 29. 13.</note> be depends, command him to go to Steeple-houſe, he goes; if they command him to pray, he prayes; if they command him to ſing, he ſings; if they bid him hear, kneel, ſit, ſtand, faſt, or feaſt, he doth it; and here he hath fellowſhip with men, and doth as his neighbours do, or with thoſe he calls brethren, if he be got into a more ſtrict form; but as for any command from God binding to theſe, or any communion with God, or anſwer of acceptance from him, upon every perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance, he looks for no ſuch thing now in theſe dayes, as though God was not now the ſame to his people that he hath been in all Ages. And thus in vain doth<note place="margin">Matth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 9.</note> he worſhip, receiving for Doctrines the commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of men, and ſo uphold and plead for a cuſtomary worſhip in a form of tradition, which he is reſolved to practiſe as long as he lives; but as for any other fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip<note place="margin">Heb<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 6. 1.</note> with God, or knowledge of him, or over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming the body of ſin, or growing up toward perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, he looks for none while he is here; but he hath ſet up his Stand as far as he intends to go, and if any go any further, or witneſs any more then he knows, he accounts it blaſphemy, and cries out againſt it, as a thing not to be ſuffered, and with carnall weapons would force all to his light; but who have eyes open ſee him to be blind.</p>
               <p>The ſecond man worſhips a God at hand<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> where he dwels in his Holy Temple, and he knowes him by his<note place="margin">John 4. 24.</note> own word from his dwelling place and not by relation<note place="margin">2 Cor. 6. 16.</note> 
                  <note place="margin">1<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Cor<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 6. 19.</note> of others, and thus the holy men of God alwayes knew him; for <hi>Abraham</hi> did not know him by what he
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:118337:7"/>
had ſpoke to <hi>Noah,</hi> nor the Prophets by what he ſpoke<note place="margin">Gen. 12. 1<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 2.</note> 
                  <note place="margin">Hoſea 1. 1.</note> to <hi>Abraham,</hi> no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Apoſtles by what he ſpoke to the<note place="margin">1 Joh. 5. 10.</note> Prophets, nor the Saints by what he ſpoke to the Apoſtles; but he that beleeveth hath the witneſs within himſelf, and thereby ſets to his ſeal that God is true, and therfore Chriſt exhorts to have ſalt in your ſelves,<note place="margin">2 Pet. 1. 19.</note> 
                  <note place="margin">Gal. 4. 6. 7.</note> and the Apoſtle exhorts the Saints to wait for the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance<note place="margin">Joh. 16. 13.</note> of Chriſt in themſelves, and to waite for the<note place="margin">Joh. 14, 26.</note> 
                  <note place="margin">John 4. 22.</note> day Star ariſing in their heart, and they knew them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves<note place="margin">1 Cor. 14. 5</note> to be the Sons of God by the Spirit that he had<note place="margin">Revel. 27. 11. 17. 29.</note> given them, and ſo doth he that is born of the Spirit, and by the ſame Spirit that witneſſeth God dwelling in him he is taught how, &amp; where, and after what maner he will be worſhipped, and he knowes what he wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips, and he worſhips in ſpirit, and he prayes in the ſpirit and ſings in the ſpirit, and with underſtanding alſo, and not in form and cuſtom, and he hath an Ear open to hear what the ſpirit ſaith, by which he is taught when and how to pray, to ſing, to faſt or Feaſt, and he Feaſteth of fat things, whereby the ſoul is nouriſhed and feeds not the luſt, he Feaſts the inward man and not the outward, for all is ſpirituall, and ſo growes in the ſpirit into neer Communion with God, and get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting<note place="margin">Rom. 8. 20.</note> 
                  <note place="margin">2 Cor. 3. 18.</note> victory over ſin the World and the Devil, and as he comes into puritie he is changed into the Image of the Lord from glory to glory, and all by the ſpirit<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </p>
               <p>The firſt man is naturall and carnal, and knowes not<note place="margin">1 Cor. 2. 14.</note> the things of God, but what he knowes naturally as bruite beaſts, and therein he doth corrupt himſelf, and doth uſe all his knowledge for corrupt ends, he boaſts of learning and tongues which are naturall, and theſe<note place="margin">Jude 10.</note> he uſeth to defraud oppreſſe and over reach the ſimple, to revenge, ſue, covet and heap together things that are
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:118337:8"/>
for corruption, and with the ſame naturall knowledge and tongues, he ſteps into the Throne of Chriſt and judges of the pure inviſible things of God, comparing ſpirituall things with carnal, and thinkes none knowes more then he, but knows nothing as he ought to know; yet with this knowledge, and that power he hath got in the earth, he ſits as judge and condemns the inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, and lets the guiltie go free, for being ſpiritually blind he takes evil good and good evil, and his ſeat is in the powers of the earth, and there he ſits as Lord from the beginning, bearing rule by his meanes, and<note place="margin">Mat. 20. 25. 26.</note> here he exerciſeth his authortie and is Heathen, and is<note place="margin">Luke 22. 53.</note> 
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 2. 6. 8.</note> Prince in the Air, and hath the powers of darkneſs<note place="margin">Jam. 1. 18.</note> committed to him; but bleſſed be the Father who hath<note place="margin">1 Pet. 1. 23.</note> 
                  <note place="margin">Col. 1. 15.</note> hid the glorious things of the Kingdom from him, and<note place="margin">Rom. 8. 29.</note> hath appointed that this Princely wiſdom of his ſhall<note place="margin">2 Pet. 3, 18.</note> 
                  <note place="margin">2 Cor. 3. 18.</note> come to naught.</p>
               <p>The ſecond man is ſpiritually begotten by the ſpirit of<note place="margin">Eph. 4. 13. 14.</note> the immortall ſeed, is the expreſſe Image of the Father, he knowes the Father, and is known of him, not by relation of the Creature, but by the in dwelling of God in him, and he in him, according to that meaſure of light revealed in him, and he ſtands in the will of God improving that he hath freely received of God, whereby he growes in the knowledge of the Father and the Son, from grace to grace, from faith to faith, till he come to the unitie of the faith and knowledge of the Son-ſhip, unto a perfect man, unto the meaſure of the ſtature of the fulneſs of Chriſt: and ſtanding faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in the leaſt meaſure, and waiting therein, the light of Chriſt under the Croſſe, and not looking out, he is kept in peace, from the craftie and ſleighty doctrines of men whereby they go about to deceive: and as the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:118337:8"/>
light growes there is a deſcerning of things that differ, to chuſe the good and refuſe the evil, and as the Son<note place="margin">John 5. 22. 27. 30.</note> ariſeth the judgement is brought forth, for all judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment<note place="margin">1 Cor. 6. 2. 3.</note> is committed to the Son, and ſo the Saints come to Judge the World, yea Angels, and are made able to try the ſpirits whether they be of God or no, and that old Serpent is judged by whom formerly they have been deceived, and ſo that which is born of God over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes<note place="margin">1 Joh. 5. 4 5.</note> the World, ſin and the devil, and is kept out of all uncleanneſs, in which the carnall minde corrupts himſelf; and thus Judgement is brought forth into victory, and the unjuſt and unclean is judged and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned and kept under within and without.</p>
               <p>The firſt man is proud and lofty, exalted above his<note place="margin">Gen. 21. 9.</note> 
                  <note place="margin">Gal. 5. 19. 20. 21.</note> brethren, a ſelf lover lives to the fleſh, and followes the luſts of the fleſh in all things, and brings forth fruits to<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the fleſh in all things, as lying, ſwearing, whoring and all manner of evil, and for a cover makes a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of godlineſs, but performs nothing but for ſelf-ends, and to be ſeen of men; but as to uprightneſs, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs and puritie, he is an enemie, a hater, a perſecuter<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> a ſcorner, a railer, unreaſonably covetous, would have all the Earth and Heaven too, would live in plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure all his life, and yet die the death of the righteous,<note place="margin">Numb. 23. 10.</note> would be an oppreſſor here and hereafter, and upon him lies all the righteous blood that hath been ſhed from the firſt, till this day.</p>
               <p>The ſecond man is humble and lowly, meek and full of love, to all, honors all men according to God with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out reſpect of perſons, would have all to come to life,<note place="margin">Ja<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 2. 1. 9.</note> ſtands in the wiſdom of God which is pure, and peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, is willing to be a fool to the World and Serpents wiſdom, content to ſuffer wrongs, buffettings, perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:118337:9"/>
ſlanders, reviling, mocking without ſeeking re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge, but bears all the venome the Serpent can caſt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him, with patience, and thereby overcomes him and<note place="margin">Gal. 5. 22.</note> bruiſeth his head<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and is made perfect through ſuffering,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 4. 17. 18.</note> and countsit joy, and rejoyceth in the Croſs, and loſs of<note place="margin">Jam. 4. 4.</note> all things<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that are viſible, but lookes at that which is Eternall, for he knowes he cannot have both, for to be a friend to the World is the enemy of God.</p>
               <p>Now all dear people judge your ſelves, if you will but deal faithfully with your ſelves, there is that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in you that wil tell you whence you are, and from whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of theſe roots all your actions proceed, for if the root be holy, the branches, &amp; fruit will be holy alſo, and by the fruits you bring forth, you may know the tree, whether you be of the firſt birth, or you be born again, and unleſs you be born again, you cannot enter into the Kingdom of Heaven, you have long time taken things upon truſt from men, and have been led blind, and brought forth fruits unto death, and have been ſervants to ſin &amp; the devil, let the time paſt be ſufficient to have wrought the will of the fleſh: and now approve your ſelves the children of God, in your actions, for by your fruits you ſhall be judged, God is holy, and his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren bear his image: Oh, redeem your time, priſe your ſouls, and minde that which is Eternall.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:118337:9"/>
               <head>III. <hi>How the ſubtiltie of the Serpent workes in the Children of diſobedience; and how he rages where he ſees the image of the Prince of Peace appear, to ſmother and ſtrangle the holy Child Jeſus.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>OThou ſubtil Serpent, why doſt thou ſo rage at the voice of the Lord, when he ſpeakes in his own, whom he hath redeemed<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and why art thou ſo mad againſt his Image where it is renewed and doth<note place="margin">Coll. 3. 10. 11.</note> appear in whom he hath begotten to himſelf? Thou haſt long uttered thy voice, in open ſtreets, by blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemous ſwearing, curſing, lying, ſlandering, railing, falſe accuſing, ſcorning, and all manner of evil ſpeaking, and haſt brought forth thy image in thy Children, in perſecuting, killing, ſtoning, mocking, impriſoning, co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetouſneſs, drunkenneſs, whoredoms, thefts and all manner of evil works and deeds of darkneſs; thou haſt long raigned as King on earth, and in earthly hearts and carnall minds, and there haſt ſhewed forth thy en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie<note place="margin">Rom. 8. 7.</note> 
                  <note place="margin">2 Theſ. 2. 4.</note> againſt God; and in ſuch thou art exalted above<note place="margin">Eſther 3. 5. 6.</note> all that is called God, and haſt got thy will upon<note place="margin">Eſther 5. 9, 13.</note> 
                  <note place="margin">Eſther 6. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>3.</note> them, and haſt brought them to fall down and worſhip thee, for that thy pride lookes much after: and as thou haſt divers colors<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſo thou lookeſt for divers kinds of worſhip; and where thou appeareſt in greateſt glory, there thou lookeſt for greateſt worſhip; and thoſe who will obey thee herein, to them thou giveſt large pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of great things in the World, and they ſhall be advanced in thy partiall Kingdom; but there is a ſeed, thou couldeſt never bring to fall down before thee, though thou haſt often attempted it, and divers wayes,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:118337:10"/>
ſometimes by great threatenings even to deſtroy the<note place="margin">Eſther 3. 6.</note> whole ſeed at one blow, as in <hi>Haman</hi> to <hi>Mordecai</hi> and all the ſeed of the Jewes becauſe he would not worſhip thee; and ſometimes by great promiſes and large diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembling proffers, as unto Chriſt the Son of God, ſhewing him all the riches of the world, and the glory thereof, ſaying, all this will I give thee if thou wilt fall<note place="margin">Mat. 6. 8. 9.</note> down and worſhip me, but this ſeed is that which is appointed to bruiſe thy head, and lay all thy pride in<note place="margin">Gen. 3. 15.</note> 
                  <note place="margin">1 King 22. 8.</note> the duſt, and the voice of this ſeed is terrible to thee<note place="margin">2 Theſ. 2. 8.</note> where it ſpeakes, for it never ſpeakes good concerning<note place="margin">Rom 8. 6.</note> 
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 7. 13.</note> thee but evil, and this ſeed is Chriſt who is riſen in his Saints, to diſcover and deſtroy thy Kingdom, by the ſword of his mouth, and by the brightneſs of his coming, for he ſpeakes death to thee where he ſpeakes, and declares the Kingdom to be death, and darkneſs, and thy works to be dead works, and that all thy ways lead to the chambers of death, and that hell, death and deſtruction are the portion of all whom thou deceiveſt, and leadeſt on in the broad way, but where ever the ſeed of God appears, it holds forth life, and leads into a way of life, works and words of life and power, for it is the light of life, and leads to life Eternal, and as this light ariſeth, it diſcovers thee, not only within, but alſo ſees thee, where thou art in the world, and is brought to lay thee open to others, and all thy deceiveable workings,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 2. 15.</note> and to judge and condemn thee; and this is the Son,<note place="margin">1<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Cor. 6. 2, 3.</note> and where he is, he is the light of the world, and judge of the World, for the Father hath committed all judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment unto the Son, and he judgeth thee in and by his Saints: And now thou ſeeſt plainly, that if he do but ſpeak and the creature hear, and beleeve, then he will diſcover all thy ſubtiltie, and redeem from under thy
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:118337:10"/>
power, by which thou haſt deceived the nations and<note place="margin">Prov. 26<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 25. 26.</note> ruled over them for many generations: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore<note place="margin">Revel. 12 13<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 15.</note> now thy deſigne is to ſtop his mouth, that he may not ſpeak under pain of impriſoning or killing the body in whom he ſpeakes, and if that will not prevail, then thou perſwadeſt people not to beleeve that it is he that ſpeakes in his own, calling it Blaſphemy for any to confeſs him, to ſpeak in them, or dwell in them now. O thou curſed crooked winding Serpent, more ſubtile<note place="margin">Joh. 9. 22.</note> 
                  <note place="margin">Joh. 6. 24.</note> then all the beaſts of the field: this was thy way a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the profeſſing wiſe knowing Jewes, when this ſeed firſt appeared in fleſh, to make them beleeve, that it was not he who was the Chriſt the Saviour of the World, he was too poor, too plain, and of too mean a ſtock, to be King of Iſrael, ye know this man from whence he is, a Carpenters Son, &amp; his kindred are with us, &amp; none beleeve on this man, but ſinners, women and Children, and a poor people that know not the Law, and they are accurſed, but when Chriſt comes, then the rulers<note place="margin">Mat. 21. 15.</note> will own him and beleeve in him: thus by perſwading<note place="margin">Joh. 7. 48. 49.</note> them to look for great things at a diſtance, a Chriſt to come who would appeare more glorious to their carnal eyes, who prevailed in them to crucifie the Son of God and Redeemer of the World. But now that the hiſtory of Chriſt being come, and hath ſuffered, and is riſen again, is generally beleeved; Now thy deſign is, to perſwade people that it is a thing paſt long ſince, and ſets them on to cry out againſt the Jews for killing of him, and Judas for betraying him, and thus ſit one of thy children to cry out againſt another, making theſe beleeve that they are in a better condition then their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, when they are all found in one and the ſame work, killing ſome, impriſoning others, mocking, ſtoning,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:118337:11"/>
beating, and ſhamefully intreating others, and to keep<note place="margin">Mat. 21. 35. 36.</note> them on in this work, perſwades them that it is not Chriſt they perſecute now, for Chriſt is in Heaven, and ſits at the right hand of God; and how can he be in his people now? he doth not appear in any now, or ſpeak<note place="margin">Gal. 1. 16.</note> 
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 11. 27.</note> in any now, neither is there any Revelations; it was ſo<note place="margin">1 Cor. 2. 14.</note> in the Apoſtles time, and the Saints of old witneſſed<note place="margin">Heb. 1. 2.</note> ſuch things; but it is blaſphemy for any now to confeſſe him, in theſe dayes: and thus thou beguileſt carnal man led by carnal reaſon, to look for a carnal Chriſt like themſelves, who can but be in one place, or perſon; as though God had now found ſome new way to ſpeak to his people and not by his Son, &amp; all this is to put out the light, leſt thou ſhouldeſt be diſcovered: for thou ruleſt in darknes, &amp; by darknes keepeſt thy poſſeſſion, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt thoſe whom thou haſt blinded; but where Chriſt is revealed and known, he is known to be ſpiritual, and not carnal, not limited to one place, but filleth heaven and earth, is all, and in all his, but not ſeen by the carnal<note place="margin">Col. 2. 10. 11.</note> 
                  <note place="margin">2 Cor. 4. 4.</note> man, though he be the light of the world; for the<note place="margin">Pſal. 58. 4, 5.</note> God of this world hath blinded the eyes of the world,<note place="margin">Eze. 4. 20. 21.</note> that they cannot ſee him, for he is a miſtery to them, and hid from all their carnal wiſdom, neither can they hear his voice, for they are not of his ſheep, but are as the deaf Adder; but to them onely in whom he dwels he is known, they hear his voice, and are taught by him alone, and will own no other voice nor teacher, and they know him to be the ſame Chriſt yeſterday, to day and for ever; the ſame who when he was to aſcend,<note place="margin">Joh. 10. 4. 5.</note> ſaid to his, if I go away, I will come again, that where<note place="margin">John 14. 3.</note> I am, there may ye be alſo; the ſame who ſaid I will<note place="margin">Col. 1. 27.</note> 
                  <note place="margin">2 Cor. 13. 3.</note> come and make mine abode with you; the ſame who<note place="margin">John 14. 6.</note> was in the Saints the hope of glory, and thoſe who have
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:118337:11"/>
him not in them are reprobates: The ſame Chriſt who ſpoke in <hi>Paul</hi> and the reſt, and they knew his voice where ever they heard it, and did obey it, though they ſuffered for it; for he was their light, their life, and their way to the Father; and by beleeving and follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him, they were led out of all the wayes of death and darkneſs, up to God into puritie and holineſs: and thus were brought to witneſs their redemption by him,<note place="margin">Mat. 11. 27.</note> 
                  <note place="margin">Gal. 1. 16.</note> and he is the ſame now to thoſe who know him, in all<note place="margin">John 10. 30.</note> things, according to the meaſure, received: he reveals<note place="margin">John 10. 4. 5.</note> 
                  <note place="margin">Pro. 8. 31.</note> himſelf now to be the Eternal Son of God, in them in<note place="margin">John 1. 3.</note> in whom he reveals the Father in them, and that<note place="margin">John 10. 20.</note> 
                  <note place="margin">John. 17. 21.</note> the Son and Father are one in him, he ſpeakes in them and by them, and they know his voice from all other voices in themſelves and others; they know his hand is not ſhortned, nor his love leſſe then it hath been to his people, and that his delight is with the ſons of men as much as ever, but it is onely in them, who love and obey him, and not their luſts, and ſuch can witneſs their fellowſhip with the Father and the Son, and they know that this is a miſtery to all the worlds wiſdom, and that the Serpents brood can no more own his voice now, where he ſpeakes, then formerly he could do, when he ſpoke in fleſh; and that he is but one in all, from the beginning to this day, and changes not: and that the Serpenr is but one in all his, though of divers colours and forms, and therefore at Wars, diſputes, and janglings among themſelves, and at envy one with another, onely they are one in this, that they all joyn to<note place="margin">Luke 23. 12.</note> 
                  <note place="margin">Revel. 9. 13.</note> perſecute the pure ſeed, in any where it appears; but where the pure ſeed appears, they are all of one colour, arayed in pure linnen white and clean, which is the righteouſneſs of Saints, and are of one heart and one
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:118337:12"/>
mind, and theſe follow the Lamb whitherſoever he<note place="margin">Revel. 19. 8.</note> goeth, never to perſecute any, but to ſuffer all the<note place="margin">Revel. 7. 14.</note> the venome, rage and malice of the Serpents brood, and are led thorow great tribulation, and have waſhed their robes, and made them white in the blood of the Lamb, and thereby they are brought to bruiſe thy head and raign above thee, and tread upon thee, and thus the promiſe of God is fulfilled in his people, and this is witneſſed in them, and they know that they are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed and ſet free from ſin and death, even by the<note place="margin">Rom. 6. 20, 21.</note> power and vertue of this ſeed, being raiſed up in them, to rule in them, and is their guide, their Judge and lawgiver, their light by which they ſee thy ſeverall deceits, whereby thou deceiveſt the nations, and keepeſt them in ſin and filthineſs, perſwading ſome, that Chriſt is come and hath redeemed them among the reſt, though they know it not, but ſtill lives in their ſins, yet if they have but a profeſſion, and go under the name of beleevers, and come before the Lord as his people, in outward performances, though they have no witneſs within themſelves yet all their ſins are ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied; for paſt, preſent and to come. And leſt they<note place="margin">1 John 5. 10.</note> ſhould doubt of it, thou ſetteſt them to the letter, to ſteal that which Chriſt in ſpirit witneſſed in the Saints, in whom he dwelt, but never yet in them; and thus by applying the promiſes of the righteous unto the wicked, encourageth them to live in ſin without fear; and this Doctrine thou broacheſt amongſt thy Ranting crew, and ſo proclaims liberty to the luſts of the fleſh, a doctrine well pleaſing to the firſt birth, and therefore ſo eaſily received, &amp; cried up by many in theſe dayes. But if the judgement of God for ſin ſeiſe upon the ſpirits of any, and they find that there can be no
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:118337:12"/>
peace with God while ſin ſtands; then thou haſt ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther way to deceive them, perſwading them that though it be ſin, and onely ſin, that breaks their peace with God, yet what power have they againſt it of themſelves? they muſt look for a day (which wil always<note place="margin">Heb. 3, 7<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note> be to come) when they ſhall have power given in an eaſie way to overcome ſin, and never take up the croſs, nor deny their own luſts, nor have their own wills cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified, and thus by tempting them to look out at re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption paſt, or to come, keeps them from minding their preſent condition, and tender of Chriſt within them, who by his light would lead them out of ſin and filthineſs, and to witneſs redemption within themſelves. Another ſort thou perſwadeſt, that none ever was, or ever ſhall be ſet free from ſin, while they are here, and that it is a vain thing ever to look for it; and that they<note place="margin">John 3. 6, 7, 8, 9,</note> are but Phariſees who ſeek to be cleaner then their neighbours, and that God is merciful, and Chriſt came to ſave ſinners: and thus Chriſt ſerves for no other end to them, but to talk on, and he who came to ſet the Saints free from ſin, and to diſcover ſin, is by thine made a cloak for ſin, and an encouragement in ſin: and further to deceive them, thou gathereſt up all the fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings of the Saints, which are written as warnings for all that come after, never to do the like, and theſe thou turneſt to encourage thine in their ſin; for this is thy curſed language, Did not <hi>David</hi> ſin? Did not <hi>Peter</hi> ſin? Did not <hi>Noah</hi> ſin? And am I better then they? And thus thou, who by ſin at firſt didſt ſtamp thy I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage on the creature, and ſo work a ſeparation betwixt God and man, ſo by ſin thou upholdeſt thy Image and<note place="margin">John 8. 44<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note> the ſeparation; for ſin is begotten by thee, and thou art the Father of it, and it bears thy Image, and the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:118337:13"/>
glory of thy kingdom ſtands in ſin and filthineſs, and thou and thy children delight in it. But wo unto<note place="margin">Dan. 12. 1.</note> thee and thy kingdom, for the day of thy tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment<note place="margin">Dan, 2. 34.</note> is upon thee: for now <hi>Michael</hi> our Prince, who ſtands up for the children and people of God, is ariſen againſt thee, who will break thee and thy Image in pieces, and thou ſhalt be caſt out of heaven, and thy Angels into the earth, and thou ſhalt be chained in the bottomleſs pit, and ſhalt deceive the nations no more; for thou art diſcovered, and the Beaſt and the falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, by whom thou haſt maintained wars againſt the Saints, and you ſhall all be caſt into the lake that bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth,<note place="margin">Rev. 20. 10.</note> there to be tormented for ever.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="part">
               <head>IV. <hi>A Caution to all who ſhall be found perſecutors, perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the righteous, not ſuffering that Spirit to ſpeak, which boldly and impartially ſpeaks without ſlaviſhneſs, being carried up above, fears not him who can kill the Body, and can do no more, but fears God.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke heed ye men of the earth, how you contend againſt the Lord, and how you ſpeak evil of the<note place="margin">Pſal. 2. 1, 2.</note> things you know not: why do ye imagine a vain thing<note place="margin">Pſal, 2, 4, 5.</note> againſt the Lord, and againſt his anointed? by your<note place="margin">Pſal 37. 13.</note> rage you ſhew your ſelves to be Heathen: He that ſits<note place="margin">Job 9. 4, 12.</note> in Heaven ſhall laugh, the Lord ſhall have you in deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, he will ſet up his King upon his holy Hill of <hi>Sion,</hi> without your leave. Did ever any ſtrive againſt God and proſper? he will break you with a rod of Iron, and daſh you in pieces like a potters veſſel; be wiſe, take heed, fear and tremble before the Lord, left his wrath
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:118337:13"/>
kindle againſt you, and you be conſumed in his anger;<note place="margin">Iſai. 45. 9.</note> 
                  <note place="margin">Iſai. 29. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> Wo to him that ſtriveth with his Maker; let the pot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheards ſtrive with the potſheards of the earth, ſhall the clay queſtion the work of the Potter? You forget your ſelves, while you are contending againſt the mind of God, you are exalted, and have forgotten that you are but duſt, and muſt to duſt again; you were not made to oppoſe the Lord in his works, but to humble your ſelves before him. And know this all yee proud ones<note place="margin">Iſai. 2. 10, 11, 12, 13, 17, 18, 19, 20, 21.</note> of the earth, that God is now exalting his own Son to be King alone upon the Throne of <hi>David,</hi> and of the<note place="margin">Iſai. 9. 6. 7.</note> increaſe of his government and peace there ſhall be no end; for he ſhall order his Kingdom himſelf in judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and juſtice for ever; but wo unto the proud at that day, for the day cometh that ſhal burn as an O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and all the proud, and all that do wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>kedly, ſhal be as ſtubble<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and the day that cometh ſhal burn them<note place="margin">Mal. 3. 2, 3.</note> up, and leave them neither root nor branch; yea, who may abide the day of his coming, and who ſhall ſtand when he appears? For he is like a Refiners fire, and Fullers ſope, and ſhal ſit as a Refiner and Purifier of ſilver, and ſhal purifie the ſons of <hi>Levy;</hi> all you muſt paſs through the fire, and all your droſs and tin muſt be conſumed, your high looks, and great ſwelling words wil be found droſs, and is for the fire. You that go a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to limit the holy one of Iſrael, what he ſhall do,<note place="margin">Job 21, 22.</note> and how he muſt make himſelfe known to his crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and by whom, God wil never come your way, for your wayes are not his wayes, nor your thoughts his thoughts, for the one are contrary to the other<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Oh<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  <note place="margin">Job 40. 2.</note> vain man, ſhal he that contendeth with the Almighty inſtruct him; he that reproveth God let him anſwer it. What art thou that queſtions the work of the Lord; or
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:118337:14"/>
his way? Thou art of that brood that came to ask Chriſt by what authority he did thoſe things his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther had ſent him to do; and becauſe thou muſt not enter into the ſecrets of God by thy Serpents wiſdom, thou wilt forbid and perſecute them in whom it is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed as they did. Now wouldſt thou but look back, and ſearch the Scriptures, thou ſhouldſt find thy gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration all along from <hi>Cain</hi> to thy ſelf, for all particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars are of that Serpents brood. It may be thou wilt<note place="margin">Gen. 4. 6.</note> own all that generation to be of <hi>Cain,</hi> til it come to thy<note place="margin">Mat. 23. 29, 30, 31.</note> ſelf, and then thou wilt deny that thou any of that brood, &amp; yet art found acting in the veryſame things; &amp; herein thou differeſt not at all from the reſt: for they would all deny it even from the firſt. For when God asked <hi>Cain</hi> where his brother was? ſaid he knew not, <hi>Am I my brothers keeper??</hi> when as he had ſlain him. And the Scribes, Phariſees, and chief Prieſts garniſhed the ſepulchres of the Prophets whom their Fathers ſlew, and ſaid, Had we lived in their dayes, we<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> would not have killed them; and at that very time were they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulting to kill the Son of God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to whom all the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets bare witneſs. But as the Divel was a murtherer from the beginning, ſo he was a lier from the beginning. But though hou wilt not own thy ſelf to be of the Divel, yet thy actions declare to thy face before Men and Angels, that thou art not of God: Did ever any that was of God forbid any to ſpeak in the name of the Lord Jeſus, whom he ſent to declare his will? Did they ever impriſon any for it? Did they ever beat, ſtone<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> mock, revile, or hate any? Did they ever raiſe lies, ſlanders, or falſe reports of any? or ſeek falſe wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes<note place="margin">Iſai. 3<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 15.</note> againſt them? Did they ever oppreſs the ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger becauſe he was a ſtranger, and ſend them to priſon
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:118337:14"/>
when they found them, becauſe they knew them not, though they never did them harm? And then to make way for their further oppreſſion, to have their Agents abroad to ſeek out any, who wil witneſs any thing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, and ſo lay ſnares and traps for the ſimple and harmleſs man. There was of thy generation in <hi>Iſaiahs</hi> time, and God plagued them for it, as ſaith the<note place="margin">Iſai. 29, 20, 21</note> Prophet, <hi>The terrible ones are brought to naught, and the ſcorners are conſumed, and all that watch for iniquity are cut off, that make a man an offender for a word, and lay a ſnare for him that reproves in the gate.</hi> Now all you that wil be found in this practice, take heed, repent betime, the righteous God wil judge righteouſly, he is no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecter<note place="margin">H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſ. 5. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> of perſons, and he knows all your ſecret plots, and who they are againſt; you may hide things from men, but wo unto them that dig deep to hide their<note place="margin">1 Pet. 1. 17.</note> counſel from the Lord, and their works are in the dark,<note place="margin">Pſal. 37. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, 13, 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, 15.</note> and they ſay, <hi>Who ſeeth us? and who knoweth?</hi> Surely<note place="margin">Iſai. 29. 13, 14.</note> your turning things upſide down, ſhall be eſteemed as the Potters clay, and God wil overturn overturn you, and bring all your plotting wiſdom to naught. O con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider what is become of the perſecuters of Old? Did not God find them out and plague them for it? and doſt thou think to eſcape his hand? Thy thoughts are vain, and wil deceive thee, the Lord will ſet a mark up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thee, thou that art a perſecuter of the meſſengers of the Lord, <hi>Go to, ſaith the Lord, write it in a book, that it</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſai. 30. 8, 9, 10, 11.</note> 
                  <hi>may be for time to come, for ever and ever, that this is a rebellious people, lying children, that will not heare the law of the Lord, which ſay to the Seers, See not, and to the Prophets, propheſie not to us right things, ſpeak unto us ſmooth things, propheſie deceit.</hi> Now ſee if it be not ſo in theſe days, he that ſtudies out eloquent words to
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:118337:15"/>
pleaſe the ears of men<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and can talk againſt ſin in words, but when they have done, joyn with the wicked in his wicked ways, as pride<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> covetouſneſs, oppreſſion, drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſs, rioting, and ſuch like, and ſo become men plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers, theſe are Prophets moſt fit for them that love their ſins<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and would not have their minds croſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>Micah</hi> ſaith<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  <note place="margin">Mica 2. 11.</note> in his days, that a lier, and one that will propheſie of wine and ſtrong drink, is a Prophet moſt fit for this people, and theſe Prophets ſhal never ſuffer perſecution, nor ever turn any from their ſins. But if any come with a true meſſage from the Lord, &amp; declare his judgments to come againſt all ſin &amp; filthineſs, and witneſs againſt all the ways of the wicked both in word and practiſe, then away with ſuch a fellow from the earth, it is not<note place="margin">Acts 22, 22.</note> fit he ſhould live, for he judgeth all but himſelf, ſend him to priſon, or into his own Countrey out of our coaſts, what hath he to do here, or who ſent him, or what is his authority? I love him not, for he never<note place="margin">1 King. 22. 8. 18.</note> ſpeaks good of us, but evil. O friend, didſt thou but know whom thou ſtriveſt againſt thou wouldſt tremble before him, it is hard for thee to kick againſt the pricks, thou art not againſt man but God. And this know, that no propheſie of old ever came by the wil of man, but againſt the wills of all men in the world, both he<note place="margin">2 Pet. 1. 21.</note> that was ſent, and they to whom he was ſent. But who hath reſiſted his wil? for there is a neceſſity laid<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> upon ſuch as are ſent by him, &amp; wo unto them if they go not. And they who are thus ſent are no Hirelings, neither do they come with <hi>What will you give me?</hi> but they<note place="margin">1 Cor. 9. 16, 17</note> muſt witneſs forth freely what Chriſt hath revealed in them, though they ſuffer for it, but this cal is not known to <hi>Babylons</hi> Merchants, who buy, ſell, and trade for mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney,<note place="margin">Revel. 18. 11.</note> neither is it known to the world, for if it were, they
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:118337:15"/>
would not hate &amp; perſecute it, but they that are ſent by<note place="margin">1 Cor. 2. 8.</note> God have b in hated in all ages, and it is the ſame now, elſe how ſhould the Scriptures be fulfilled, but O man take heed what thou doeſt, thy power is limitted though thou know it not, thou canſt but kill the bodie, and the ſoul ſhall live, thou canſt but impriſon the body,<note place="margin">Mat. 10. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> and the ſpirit is at liberty out of thy reach, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Chriſt bids his not to fear ſuch, who can go no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and it is ſo, for they who are kept cloſe in obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to Chriſt are kept out of the fear of man, for ſaith<note place="margin">Iſa. 51. 12. 13. 14.</note> the Lord, I even I am he that comforted you, who art thou that thou ſhouldſt be afraid of a man that ſhal die, and the Son of man that ſhall be as graſſe, &amp; forgetteth the Lord thy Maker<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that hath ſtretcheth forth the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens<note place="margin">Iſa. 51. 16.</note> laid the foundations of the earth, &amp; hath feared every day becauſe of the fury of the oppreſſor, as if he were ready to deſtroy, and where is the fury of the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſor; but ſaith the Lord I have put my words into thy mouth, &amp; have covered thee with the ſhadow of my hand, behold I have taken out of thy hand the Cup of my fury, and thou ſhalt no more drink it again, but I will put it into the hand of them that afflict thee, which ſay to thy ſoul, bow down that we may go over thee, and thou haſt laid thy body, as the ground, and as the<note place="margin">Iſa. 14. 10.</note> ſtreet, to them that go over, therefore take heed you that tread the poor and helpleſſe under your feet, repent repent, your day is coming on a pace, wherein the Lord wil avenge the poor on him that is too ſtrong for him, and how canſt thou ſtand at the day, when thou ſhalt become weak, as another man, and no falſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences will be accepted, thou muſt be Judged accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to thy works good or evil, Oh that you had hearts to humble your ſelves, before the Lord, that ye might find mercy at that day, for why will you periſh rough your own will.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="part">
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:118337:16"/>
               <head>V. <hi>A call to the world, to repentance, and the curſed condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that men lie in, profeſsing much but practiſing juſt nothing but pride, wantonneſs, covetouſneſs, and yet cover themſelves with large profeſsions, and call themſelves Saints, wo, wo to all them who profeſs the truth, and live in unrightneſs and that turne the grace of God into wantonneſs.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>ALl people repent and turn to the Lord from the evil of your doing, for the Lord is at hand who<note place="margin">Iſa. 3. 10. 11.</note> will judge the world, and give every one according to<note place="margin">Iſa. 26. 21.</note> 
                  <note place="margin">2 Theſ 1. 7. 8. 9</note> their doings whether they be good or evil, yea he is<note place="margin">1 John 3. 6.</note> coming with ten thouſands of his Angels, to be avenged on the Heathen and them that know not God, now all that live in ſin &amp; filthineſs, it plainly appears you know not God, for if you did, you durſt not heap iniquitie and live in your luſts heaping up wrath againſt the day of wrath, wherein the Lord will appear as a conſuming fire, againſt all ungodlineſs of wicked men.</p>
               <p>God is againſt you, you diſſembling profeſſors, who adorn the outſide, to be ſeen of men, but the inſide is full of deceit, ſerving God in outſide forms and noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,<note place="margin">Mat. 23. 25, 26, 27, 28.</note> but your hearts are not upright with him, you are in the earth, and earthly mindedneſs, in your cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſs, which is Idolatry, and God abhors the outſide worſhip: when the heart is not upright with him, and Chriſt cals ſuch, whited wals painted ſepulchres, hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites, Serpents, a generation of vipers, children of the<note place="margin">Mat. 23. 33.</note> devil, and the woe is to ſuch, how can you eſcape the damnation of hell.</p>
               <p>God is againſt you: you proud and luſtfull wanton ones, who make it your greateſt care to deck your ſelves,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:118337:16"/>
your proud atire, inventing new wayes and<note place="margin">Iſa. 28. 12, 34.</note> faſhions to make your ſelves glorious in the ſight of men, that they may bow down and worſhip you, and ſet you above the Commands of God, but know that<note place="margin">Iſa 2. 10. 11. 17</note> you are but duſt, and God will lay ſuch honour in the<note place="margin">Iſa. 16. to the end.</note> duſt, for he is riſen to whom all worſhip is due, and now wo to all the idols of the world, your lofty looks ſhall be humbled, and your haughtineſs bowed down, for now the Lord will exalt the humble and meek ones, that you have troden upon, he will ſeek that<note place="margin">Ezek. 34<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 16.</note> which is loſt, but will deſtroy the fat, and feed the<note place="margin">Luke 6 24.</note> ſtrong with judgement; repent you lofty ones and turn to the Lord, and humble your ſelves before him that you may be hid in the day of his fierce wrath leaſt he take you away, and there be none to deliver.</p>
               <p>God is againſt you, you drunkards, who make it your trade to pour in ſtrong drink, abuſing the creature to ſatisfie you luſts, which God hath given to be uſed<note place="margin">Iſa. 28. 1. 3.</note> 
                  <note place="margin">Joel 1. 5.</note> moderately and not in riotouſneſs, you ſhould be rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable<note place="margin">Iſa. 5. 22.</note> creatures, but your horſe may teach you, who will not drink when he hath enough, and here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in you ſhew your ſelves worſe then bruits, and they ſhall riſe up in Judgement againſt you and condemn you, woe to you that are mighty to drink wine, and<note place="margin">Iſa. 5. 11.</note> 
                  <note place="margin">Hab. 2. 15. 16.</note> men of ſtrength to mingle ſtrong drink, wo to you that riſe up early that you may follow ſtrong drink and continue untill night, till wine inflame them, the wo is upon you that put the cup to his neighbours mouth, to make him drink that his makedneſs may appear, and ſhamefull ſpuing cover him, and this is your glory, which is your ſhame, and you tell your companions, you ſhew your ſelves to be the children of <hi>Ham,</hi> the<note place="margin">Gen. 9, 22 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> father of <hi>Canaan,</hi> who was accurſed for ſuch practiſe, and the curſe is upon you, while you live in this, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:118337:17"/>
repent, and live no longer in your filthineſs, your healths is abomination to the Lord, and you are igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of his ſaving health; the wants of the poor cries in the ears of God, againſt your waſtfull practiſe, and you muſt account for your ſtewardſhip.</p>
               <p>God is againſt you: you ſwearers, who make it your practiſe to take the name of God in vain, and live in<note place="margin">Pro. 19. 29.</note> 
                  <note place="margin">Prov. 3. 34.</note> open breach of his commands, you who are not<note place="margin">Jer. 23. 10.</note> aſhamed to profane the holy name of God in open<note place="margin">Zach. 5. 3.</note> 
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 5 34. 35.</note> ſtreets and houſes where you come, the curſe is upon the<note place="margin">Jam. 5. 12.</note> Land for your ſakes, and becauſe of oathes the Land<note place="margin">Pſal 9. 17.</note> mournes, and God will not hold you guiltleſſe, repent<note place="margin">Jer. 5. 7.</note> repent, the curſe is towards you; you profane ones who regards not the commands of Chriſt, who ſaith ſwear not at all, but let your yea be yea, and your nay nay, for whatſoever is more cometh of evil, how is he your Redeemer, and how will you ſtand before him, at the day of Judgement, whom you now ſo openly contemn, in diſobeying his commands, O Repent, the day is at hand when it will be too late.</p>
               <p>God is againſt you: you ſcorners, who take delight in ſcorning your brethen, you ſhew your folly to all,<note place="margin">Iſa. 18. 14, 15, 18.</note> and whoſe children you are, you that ſit in the ſeat of the ſcornfull, God doth ſcorn you, He who ſits in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven laughs you to ſcorn, you are proud and puft up and have ſcornfull eyes, you that raiſe falſe reports againſt<note place="margin">Luke 6. 25.</note> the ſimple and tell them to make your ſelves and others laugh, that are ſcorners like you: the Lord will laugh<note place="margin">Iſa. 14. 11. 12.</note> at your calamitie, and mock when your fear cometh, your laughter ſhall be turned into mourning, wo to them that now laugh, for they ſhall mourn, you for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get your ſelves what you are, take heed be not mockers,<note place="margin">Iſa. 28. 22.</note> leaſt your bands be made ſtrong, and when you cry
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:118337:17"/>
there be none to deliver take heed repent betime, how<note place="margin">Prov. 1<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 22.</note> long will you ſcorners delight in ſcorning and fools<note place="margin">Iſa. 57. 34. 5.</note> hate knowledge, ceaſe your ſports and paſtimes you wanton ones, making your ſelves merry in your ſins, your idle profane talking and fooliſh Jeſting, your un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean filthy words are abomination to the Lord, and every idle word muſt be accounted for, your reveling, and rioting, Carding, and dicing, and all your invented ſports, ſitting down to eat and drink and riſing up to play, which is idolatry, and the wrath of God is againſt<note place="margin">1 Cor. 10, 7.</note> ſuch practiſe, for man was not made to fulfill his own<note place="margin">Iſa 22. 12. 13. 14.</note> luſts, but to ſerve the living God, who made all things for himſelf and the wicked for the day of Judgement,<note place="margin">Pro. 16. 4. 5.</note> 
                  <note place="margin">Job 21. 30.</note> and they are reſerved againſt the day of wrath and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction,<note place="margin">Pro. 11. 21.</note> and though hand joyn in hand, the wicked ſhall not go unpuniſhed; repent, take heed, ſearch the Scriptures, if ever the people of God uſed any ſuch practiſe, or ſpent his time after that manner, but la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured to redeem the time, and had there crucified with the affections and luſts, for they who live to the fleſh cannot pleaſe God.</p>
               <p>God is againſt you: you covetous cruell oppreſſors, who grind the faces of the poor and needie taking your<note place="margin">Pro. 11. 1.</note> advantage of the neceſſities of the poor, falſifying the<note place="margin">Iſa. 3. 15.</note> meaſures and uſing deceitful weights, ſpeaking that by your commodities which is not true, and ſo deceiving<note place="margin">Iſa. 5. 8. 9.</note> the ſimple, and hereby getting great Eſtates in the world, laying houſe to houſe, &amp; Land to Land, till their be no place for the poor, and when they are become poor through your deceits, then you diſpiſe them, and exalts your ſelves above them, and forgets that you are all made of one mould and one blood, and muſt all appear before one judge, who is no reſpecter
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:118337:18"/>
of perſons, nor doth he deſpiſe the poor, and what<note place="margin">Acts 17. 26.</note> ſhall your riches avail you at that day, when you muſt<note place="margin">Gal. 2. 6.</note> account how you have gotten them, and whom you have oppreſſed, yea wo to him that coveteth an evil covetouſneſs to his own houſe, that buildeth a houſe with oppreſſion, the ſtone in the wall and the beam in<note place="margin">Hab. 2. 11. 12.</note> the timber ſhall crie out againſt him, The fathers com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit crueltie and oppreſſion in heaping together, and the children commit filthineſs in ſpending it upon their luſts, and thus the children eat up the ſins of their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and fill up the meaſure of their fathers iniquitie,<note place="margin">Mat. 23. 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> and thus you make an open gap for the wrath of God to break in upon you, Oh repent and turn unto the Lord that there may be one found to ſtand in the gap and make up the breach, leaſt the wrath of God break in upon you, and burn like fire and there be none to quench it, for the day of the Lord is at hand, that you muſt all be weighed in the pure balance of the Sanctua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry<note place="margin">Dan. 5<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 25.</note> and nothing will be weight, but what is pure and holy, truth from the heart, no deceit nor hypocriſie will be weight, no peace by a drunkard, or whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongers will be weight, no idolators, proud, or covet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, no ſwearer, lyer, drunkard, or whoremonger, will be<note place="margin">Revel. 23. 13.</note> weight, no Idolators, proud or covetous ones no ſcorner railer, or falſe accuſers, no murtherer nor envious perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuter, no fornicator, nor unclean ones, nor any that lives to the fleſh can be weight, but wil be found wanting, and then wo unto you, for your kingdom muſt be taken from you and given to them who will bring forth fruits that God may have glory: now all profeſſors and people conſider your conditions, you have been long hearers and profeſſors, but what have your fruits been, herein is<note place="margin">Mat. 3. 10.</note> my Father glorified that you bring forth much fruit; but now you fruitleſs trees you muſt be cut down and
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:118337:18"/>
caſt into the fire, for all mens works muſt be tried by<note place="margin">1 Cor. 3. 13.</note> fire, and then wo unto you who have taken pleaſure in ſin, repent, and return to the Lord betime, that you may find mercy, for your deſtruction is of your ſelves.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="part">
               <head>VI. <hi>The curſed condition of conceited ones, who are wiſe in their own eyes.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>VVO unto you that are wiſe in your own eyes,<note place="margin">Iſai. 5. 21.</note> and prudent in your own ſight, you that think<note place="margin">Iohn 14. 17.</note> to underſtand the ſpirituall things of God by your car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal<note place="margin">Iude 10.</note> wiſdom; and becauſe God wil not reveal his ſecrets to your ſerpentine wiſdom, therefore you ſpeak evil of it where it is revealed, though you know it not; your wiſdom is of the earth, and feedeth upon duſt, and duſt is the Serpents meat: by your wiſdom you can over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reach<note place="margin">Iſai. 65. 25.</note> your brethren, oppreſs the poor to get riches, to make your ſelves great in the earth, and thereby Lord it over your brethren, by it you can go to law, and begger your poor brethren for trifles, to fulfil your own wils, by it you can deceive the ſimple and harmleſs man, and make him your laughing-ſtock when you have done, by it you can contrive miſchief on your bed, and when the morning is come you put in practice againſt thoſe whom you envy. And do you think that ever God wil<note place="margin">Mica 2. 1, 2, 3.</note> reveal himſelf to this wiſdom, any other wayes then in wrath from heaven againſt all ungodlineſs and unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs of this wiſdom; nay, the ſecrets of the Lord are with them that fear him, but there is no fear of the Lord where this wiſdom ruleth. But you are puft up in your vain mind, &amp; think you know much, when as you know nothing yet as you ought to know? For (ſaith the Apoſtle,) <hi>Who is a wiſe man amongst you, and en</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 1. 18.</note>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:118337:19"/>
                  <hi>dued with knowledge, let him ſhew out of a good converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iam. 3. 13.</note> 
                  <hi>his works with meekneſs of wiſdom.</hi> Your works that proceed out, ſhew plainly what kind of wiſdom is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, that wiſdom that brings forth pride, ſcorning, light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and wantonneſs, ſwearing, lying, covetouſneſs, ſelf-love,<note place="margin">Iob 14. 4.</note> envy, hatred, deceit, backbiting, ſlandering, and evill ſpeaking, luſt &amp; exceſs, ſtrife and contention, perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or any other unclean or filthy practice, doing to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers that w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> you would not have them to do to you; that wiſdom is of the Divel, and not of God. Now this is the wiſdom the world drives after, and ſo highly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tols, and by which you think to attain to the pure and inviſible things of God. And thus the wiſdome of the Serpent, which riſeth out of the earth, and feedeth on earth, would be climbing up to the hidden things of God, and ſo would be heirs of two Kingdoms. But ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>If ye have bitter envyings and ſtrife in your hearts, glory not, and lye not againſt the truth.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iam. 3. 14, 15, 16.</note> This wiſdom deſcends not from above, but is earthly, ſenſual, and diveliſh. For where envy and ſtrife is, there is confuſion and every evil work: but that wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom which is from above, is firſt pure, then peaceable, gentle, and eaſie to be entreated, ful of mercy and good fruits, without partiality, without hypocriſie. Now you<note place="margin">Iam. 3. 17.</note> who think you are the men for wiſdom, try your wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom by theſe marks ſet down by the Apoſtle, whether it be given you from above, or it be of the Serpent, ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing out of the earthly part within you. Is it ſuch a wiſdom as ſhews forth of a good co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>verſation, the works of meekneſs? Is it pure? Is it peaceable? Is it gentle, and eaſie to be intreated? Is it full of mercy and good fruits? without partiality &amp; without hypocriſie? If it bring forth theſe fruits, it is from above, and God will
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:118337:19"/>
own it, &amp; reveal his ſecrets to it, even the hidden things of God. But on the contrary, if it be that wiſdom that<note place="margin">Jam. 3. 15.</note> brings forth bitter envyings and ſtrife, and every evil work, vainglorying, and lying againſt the truth, the Apoſtle ſaith plainly, It is not of God, but is earthly, ſenſual, and diveliſh; and this wiſdom muſt never enter into the kingdom, but is of the Serpent, curſed above all creatures, more ſubtile then all the beaſts of the field, eating the forbidden fruit, the judging of good and evil by carnal knowledge, creeping into the earth, &amp; earthly things, all for the belly, feeding on duſt, and delighting in things that periſh and fade away, painted on the outſide, decking thee with pride, curiouſly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented (Scrpent-like) by this wiſdom, and feeding thy luſt with curious deviſed diſhes, <hi>Dives</hi>-like, deviſing and plotting to get riches right or wrong, ſo that you can but keep within the compaſs of the laws of the nation, never regarding to be guided by that pure law of God within, written in the heart, which would lead<note place="margin">Heb. 10. 16.</note> 
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 8. 7.</note> you in all things to do as you would be done by. But the wiſdom of men is not ſubject to the law of God, neither can be, for it is death to it, and you deceive your ſelves, who did think to find out the myſtery of the things of God by this wiſdom, for God hath hid it from your eyes; and the world by wiſdom knows<note place="margin">1 Cor, 1. 20, 21.</note> not God, for God hath turned their wiſdom into foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhneſs: And, ſaith Chriſt, <hi>I thank thee, O Father, Lord of Heaven and earth, that thou haſt hid theſe things from</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Matth. 11. 25.</note> 
                  <hi>the wiſe and prudent, and revealed them to Babes.</hi> God<note place="margin">Iohn 3. 5, 6<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note> hath hid them in Chriſt, and none comes to Chriſt but Babes, ſuch are of the new birth, not fleſh and blood, but of water and the ſpirit, ſuch onely enter into the myſtery of the Kingdom, by the Door in all the
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:118337:20"/>
ſtrait way, through the Croſs, where your Serpents wiſdom would not willingly come; for if it do, it muſt be ſlain, and you muſt become fools for Chriſts ſake,<note place="margin">Luke 18. 17.</note> that you may be wiſe, you muſt enter as a little child, or elſe you cannot come there; for it is revealed to Babes onely; your wiſdom that you ſo much boaſt on, muſt be crucified and die, and a new wiſdom muſt<note place="margin">Job 8. 28.</note> be given you from above, which begins with the fear of the Lord; for the fear of the Lord is the beginning of wiſdom, and to practice it is underſtanding: and when you once come to own this true Wiſdom which is of God, then you ſhall ſee the world, who did ſo highly applaud you for your wiſdom, before, will now call you fools and madmen, for that wiſdom which they do applaud ſhall be caſt behind thee, and then thou ſhalt witneſs the Scripture fulfilled, when God hath deſtroyed the wiſdom of the wiſe, and brought to<note place="margin">1 Cor. 1. 19. 20. 21.</note> nought the underſtanding of the prudent, where is the wiſe, where is the diſputer of this world? for the world by this wiſdom knowes not God nor ever ſhall do; for God hath choſen the fooliſh things of this world to confound the wiſe, and weak things to confound the<note place="margin">1 Cor. 1. 25. 27</note> mighty, &amp; then thou ſhalt ſee that wiſdom, not to be of<note place="margin">1 Cor. 2. 6. 7. 8.</note> this world, neither of the Princes of this world, which come to nought, but the wiſdom of God which is a hidden myſterie, which none of the Princes of this world knew; for if they knew it, they would not perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute it, where it is, but the knowledge of this myſtery is the free gift of God, given onely to them who fear and love him, given without all naturall helpes what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 2. 14. 15</note> for the naturall man receives not the things of the ſpirit of God, for they are fooliſhneſs to him, neither can he know them, for they are ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:118337:20"/>
diſcerned, but the ſpirituall man Judgeth all things, and he himſelf is Judged of no man, for he that is in the ſpirit lives above all the earth and<note place="margin">Coloſ. 3. 3.</note> earthly wiſdom, and ſees all the world, where they live, but no carnal wiſdom ſhall ever ſee where he lives, for his life is hid with God in Chriſt from all vultures eyes, and venomous beaſts,</p>
            </div>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>James Nayler</hi> a priſoner of the Lord, to all that names the name of the Lord to whom theſe ſhall come, deſires Grace and Peace.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
